Cosmopolitan Club records, 1916-1970 C237
Indiana University Archives
Cosmopolitan Club records
1916-1970
1922-1958
Indiana University Archives
Association of Cosmopolitan Clubs in the American Universities. Indiana University Chapter
C237
.6 cubic feet 1 box; 2 oversize folders
The Indiana University Cosmopolitan Club was founded in 1916 and received its charter from the Corda Fratres Association of Cosmopolitan Clubs in 1918. The Club was dedicated to fostering understanding and fraternity between foreign and American students in order to promote international cooperation and peace. The collection consists of correspondence, programs, financial records, membership lists, and newspaper clippings. Also included are publications, including issues of the Club newsletter, the Cosmo reporter.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Advance notice is required.
Historical Note
The Corda Fratres Association of Cosmopolitan Clubs was founded at the University of Wisconsin in 1904, out of an International Club that had formed in 1903. The Corda Fratres Association of Cosmopolitan Clubs began to expand to other Universities and started to hold national conventions of the Cosmopolitan Club chapters in 1907. The first convention was held at the University of Wisconsin in Madison. A Cosmopolitan Club member from the University of Wisconsin, Louis Luchner, wrote to President Bryan in October and November of 1907, inviting Indiana University to form an International or Cosmopolitan Club in order to attend the first convention.
This attempt was unsuccessful; however, an Indiana University chapter of the Cosmopolitan Club was founded nine years later, on November 19, 1916, by 12 international students. The original constitutional committee consisted of: T.V. Petranoff (Bulgaria), Heinman Blatt (Russia), Y. Kodera (Japan), and Club President, J.T. Hsi (China). The Indiana University Cosmopolitan Club adopted a constitution on December 9, 1916 and received a charter from the Corda Fratres Association of Cosmopolitan Clubs on January 1, 1918.
On December 26-29, 1923, Indiana University hosted the 17th annual National Convention with 77 delegates of 15 different nationalities registered in attendance. This same year, the Indiana University chapter was the executive chapter for all Cosmopolitan Clubs in the United States. In conjunction with this honor, I.U. history professor, Dr. James A. Woodburn, was elected national president of the Corda Fratres Association of Cosmopolitan Clubs. Additional Cosmopolitan Club faculty advisors of note at Indiana University include Leo R. Dowling in the 1940's and Walter E. Burnham in the 1950's and 1960's.
As illustrated by the club motto, "Above all nations is humanity," the Cosmopolitan Club was founded to foster understanding and fraternity between foreign and American students, in order to promote international cooperation and world peace. Throughout its existence at Indiana University, the Cosmopolitan Club strove to maintain a 50/50 balance of U.S. and international members. By 1965, the club membership roster for the Indiana University chapter documented a membership of 515 individuals, representing 54 different countries.
On March 25, 1922, the Indiana Daily Student reported on the first 'International Revue' (held March 24, 1922), marking the beginning of the Cosmopolitan Club's long tradition of presenting international dance, music and culture to the Indiana University community. The international performances and socials led to the development of an annual International Dinner, coinciding with a week of exhibitions and activities celebrating the United Nations. The first of these dinners was held in 1953 and they continued for 16 years. The International Dinner proved to be one of the most popular and widely attended activities of the club.
Through out the 1950's and early 1960's, interest in the Cosmopolitan Club remained high, as illustrated by events programming, newsletters, and membership rosters. By 1969, however, events and publications had waned and only 6 members were pictured in the Arbutus yearbook. 1969 was the last year the club was pictured in the Arbutus, but the collection contains an invitation to the 1970 International Dinner, indicating that the club remained active after ceasing to appear in the Arbutus. This document, dated February 12, 1970, is the last transaction of Cosmopolitan Club activity in the collection.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: Subject files and Scrapbook.
Scope and Content Note
This collection documents the formation and activities of the Indiana University Cosmopolitan Club chapter from 1916-1970, with most of the material dating from the 1920s through the 1960s. Types of material in the collection include meeting minutes, constitutions, and by-laws; newspaper clippings, correspondence, event programs and invitations, financial reports, membership directories. Similar material is contained in a disassembled scrapbook (1921-1943) of clippings, photographs, meeting minutes, membership rosters, financial records, club constitution and by-laws, event programs and posters, and correspondence. Publications in the collection include an incomplete run of the Cosmo Reporter, the official newsletter of the IU Cosmopolitan Club chapter, the issues of which contain news and announcements and interest pieces on specific students and other countries and cultures.
The collection is organized into two series: Subject files and Scrapbook.
Separated Material
Duplicates removed from collection.
Related Material
Related photographs may be available in the IU Archives Photograph Collection.
The IU Archives also holds an additional Cosmopolitan Club scrapbook (Accession 0195), which could not be located at the time of processing.
Acquisition Information
Accession 0454, reference files, and publications
Students, Foreign --Indiana --Bloomington --Societies, etc.; College students --Indiana --Bloomington --History --20th century --Sources.; Student publications --Indiana --Bloomington.; College students' writings --Indiana --Bloomington.; Cosmo reporter.; Association of Cosmopolitan Clubs in the American Universities. Indiana University Chapter -- History -- Sources; Association of Cosmopolitan Clubs in the American Universities. Indiana University Chapter -- Records and correspondence; Association of Cosmopolitan Clubs in the American Universities. Indiana University Chapter -- Archives; Indiana University -- students -- Social life and customs
- Subject Files, 1916-1970; undated
  - Administrative documents, 1924-1941; undated (Box 1)
    Scope and Content Note
    This file include extracts of meeting minutes from February to April, 1924 and May 1925; a 1924 club initiation ritual; and various drafts of the national and local Cosmopolitan Club constitutions and by-laws.
  - Charter, Cosmopolitan Club of Indiana University, January 1, 1918; (oversize) (Box OS5)
  - Clippings, 1916-1958; undated (Box 1)
    This file contains Indiana Daily Student articles that cover the formation and activities of the Cosmopolitan Club as well as interest stories about international students and international issues, in general.
  - Correspondence, 1922-1967; undated (Box 1)
    This file contains communication between club officers and members; the faculty advisors, Leo R. Dowling and Walter E. Burnham; participants in events, such as the International Dinner; and general correspondence informing members of meetings and events.
  - Corda Fratres Association of Cosmopolitan Clubs publications, 1922-1923 and circa 1920s (Box 1)
  - Cosmo Reporter brochure, 1922-1923; (4 copies) (Box 1)
  - Cosmo Reporter newsletter (Box 1)
    - 1923-1926 (Box 1)
    - 1927-1928 (Box 1)
    - 1949 (Box 1)
    - 1950 (Box 1)
    - 1957-1958 (Box 1)
    - 1961, 1965, and circa 1960s (Box 1)
  - Events, 1922-1970; undated (Box 1)
    The Events file includes programs for various events, including the first International Revue, March 24, 1922 and the 17th annual convention of the Corda Fratres Association. It also contains invitations to numerous events, such as the International Dinners, Movie Nights; receptions; open houses; and meetings. There is also a great deal of planning material related to the International Dinners, including committee reports, hand-written notes, tickets, and flyers. Additional items of interest in this file are a guestbook from the 1923 convention and schedules of several trips arranged by the Cosmopolitan Club in the 1950s.
  - Financial records, 1922-1958; undated (Box 1)
    The Financial records file includes one receipt from 1922, a preliminary draft of a financial summary for January through May 1923, two documents from 1924 and 1928 relating to the Cosmopolitan Club Loan Fund for foreign students, a ledger and treasury report from 1955, a financial report for the 1957-1958 school year, instructions to treasurers of student organizations, and an undated, hand-written account of members who paid for a picnic event.
  - Initiation, circa 1938 (Box 1)
  - Membership Files, 1963-1966; undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous publications and drafts, 1922-1965; undated (Box 1)
- Scrapbook, 1921-1943; undated
  This series consists of the remains of an original scrapbook. This scrapbook has been disassembled and partially photocopied due to poor condition and acidification, so facsimiles of newspaper clippings from 1921-1928 and some pages of the scrapbook follow the original items. These remaining original items include photographs, meeting minutes, membership rosters, financial records, the constitution and by-laws, event programs and posters, and correspondence – including a condolence letter to first lady, Mrs. Warren G. Harding, upon the death of the President and a response from the White House.
  - Original items, 1922-1923 (Box 1)
  - Original items, 1924-1927 (Box 1)
  - Original itemsand, 1941-1943; undated (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1921-1928; (photocopies) (Box 1)
  - Posters, 1923, 1945; (oversize) (Box OS3)
    - International Revue by the Cosmopolitan Club: The Phoenix, 1923 (Box OS3)
    - Good Will Show, 1945 (Box OS3)